Let’s talk about the use of the word “which” and the word “that”.
Hãy bàn về cách sử dụng từ "which" và từ "that".
Generally, the word WHICH, with a comma before it, is used when the content following the
Thông thường, từ WHICH, có dấu phẩy ở trước, được sử dụng khi nội dung theo sau
word “which” isn&#39;t necessary for the understanding of the sentence.
từ "which" không quan trọng trong câu.
The word THAT, without a comma before it, is used to show the significance of that description.
Từ "THAT", khi không có dấu phẩy đằng trước nó, dùng để biểu thị nội dung quan trọng trong câu.
For example:
Ví dụ như
“The bucket of water, WHICH has a thermometer, is temperature controlled.”
“The bucket of water, WHICH has a thermometer, is temperature controlled.”
versus “The bucket of water THAT has a thermometer is temperature controlled.”
so với “The bucket of water THAT has a thermometer is temperature controlled.”
In the second sentence, it’s important to know that the presence of the thermometer
Trong trường hợp thứ 2, tình trạng hiện tại của chiếc nhiệt kế (thermometer) quan trọng hơn.
tells us which bucket is temperature controlled.
nó giúp chúng ta biết chiếc xô đã được kiểm soát nhiệt độ
The first sentence does not suggest that having a thermometer is a UNIQUE aspect of that bucket.
Trường hợp 1  không thể hiện rằng việc "having a thermometer" ( có 1 chiếc nhiệt kế ) là đặc điểm đặc biệt của cái xô nước đó
Now, it&#39;s important to note that the word THAT isn&#39;t needed in the sentence in some
Tuy nhiên, trong nhiều trường hợp, từ "that" cũng bị coi là dư thừa
cases.
cases.
For example:
Ta lấy ví dụ sau:
The sentence: “The research THAT was conducted in 2004 provided support for the idea.”
“The research THAT was conducted in 2004 provided support for the idea.”
versus “The research conducted in 2004 provided support for the idea.”
So với “The research conducted in 2004 provided support for the idea.”
Leaving the word THAT out in the second sentence makes the sentence less wordy and more concise.
Việc lược bỏ "that" ở trường hợp thứ 2 làm câu văn gọn gàng và chính xác hơn.
Apart from knowing when to use and not to use the word WHICH and the word THAT, it’s
Ngoài việc nắm rõ cách sử dụng "WHICH", "THAT"
also important that we pay attention to how we use our pronouns.
Chúng ta cũng cần chú ý về cách sử dụng đại từ
Now remember?
Các bạn còn nhớ chứ?
A pronoun is any word that stands in place of a noun, like, he, she, it, or they.
Đại từ là từ có thể thay thế cho danh từ, ví dụ như "she,he,it, they"
When we misuse pronouns, we could create confusion for the reader.
Khi chúng ta dùng sai, ta có thể gây lúng túng cho độc giả
For example, if we wrote, “The students left their notes in the lecture theatre.
Lấy ví dụ “The students left their notes in the lecture theatre.
They were too busy chatting.”
They were too busy chatting.”
Does this mean the notes were too busy chatting or the students were too busy chatting?
Nó có nghĩa là những tờ giấy ghi chú ( "the notes" ) hay là những học sinh ( "the students" )đang rất bận rộn tám chuyện?
Because, the word “They” could be linked to the noun “notes” or to the noun “students”.
Bởi vì từ "they" vừa có thể bổ nghĩa cho "notes" hoặc "students".
Rewriting these sentences as “The students left their notes in the lecture theatre.
Ta có thể viết lại câu như sau "“The students left their notes in the lecture theatre.The students were too busy chatting”
The students were too busy chatting” makes it very clear who the noun is that we’re
Câu sẽ có nghĩa rõ ràng hơn
referring to.
về chủ thể của hoạt động đang nói đến
Now sometimes, people like to begin a sentence with the word “there”, like “there were”,
Tiếp theo, thỉnh thoảng mọi người thường hay bắt đầu câu với "there", như "there were"
“there are”, or “there was”.
“there are”, hoặc “there was”.
Generally speaking, we should avoid starting a sentence with the word “there”, as in
Nguyên tắc chung, ta nên tránh viết dạng này càng nhiều càng tốt
most cases, words like “there were”, “there are”, or “there was” are not needed
Những từ như “there were”, “there are”, hoặc or “there was” thực sự không cần thiết
at the beginning of a sentence.
khi viết đầu câu
For example, people sometimes write: “There was good evidence to support these predictions”.
Hãy đến với 1 ví dụ  “There was good evidence to support these predictions”.
This sentence can simply be rewritten as “Good evidence supported these predictions”.
Câu trên có thể viết lại đơn giản hơn “Good evidence supported these predictions”.
The last issue I would like to talk about is the apostrophe.
Vấn đề cuối cùng tôi muốn đề cập là dấu lược
People are often confused with how they should be using it.
Đây là vấn đề mà mọi người thường lúng túng khi sử dụng
The apostrophe with the letter “s” is a type of punctuation used to indicate the
Dấu lược đi với "s"
possession of nouns and pronouns.
thường ám chỉ nghĩa sở hữu của danh từ hoặc đại từ
It indicates ownership or that one thing belongs to another.
Nó mang nghĩa sở hữu của 1 vật với vật kia
For singular possessive nouns, like RESEARCHER, we simply add the apostrophe and “s” at
Với đanh từ số ít, ví dụ RESEARCHER
the end of the word, like “The researcher’s data”, when we’re describing the data
Ta thêm "s" ngay sau nó, ví dụ “The researcher’s data” khi chúng ta
that belongs to a single researcher.
muốn diễn đạt số liệu đó thuộc về nhà nghiên cứu
For plural nouns, on the other hand, they already end with the letter “s”, like
Đối với danh từ số nhiều - danh từ đã có "s" ở cuối
RESEARCHERS.
Ví dụ: RESEARCHERS.
So, in order to indicate the data belongs to more than one researcher, we add the apostrophe
Vậy nên để chỉ số liệu thuộc về nhiều nhà nghiên cứu,
AFTER the “s”.
chúng ta thêm dấu lược SAU "s'
For example, “The researchers’ data”.
Ví dụ “The researchers’ data”.
However, when we write the word “it’s”, “it’s” written this way is a CONTRACTION
Tuy nhiên, khi chúng ta viết "it's", it's" là 1 cách viết tắt
of “it is”.
của “it is”.
When we write “it’s”, we are not communicating the possession of “it”.
Khi viết “it’s”, chúng ta không đề cập đến sự sở hữ của “it”.
The possessive form of “it” is written as “its”.
Tính từ sở hữu của it là "its"
For example, “Its findings”.
Ta lấy ví dụ “Its findings”.
So, these are the common mistakes people make when writing.
Tóm lại, chúng ta đã đi qua một số lỗi thường mắc phải khi viết luận
Be mindful of YOUR writing, and try to avoid making these mistakes.
Hãy cẩn thận và cố gắng tránh lặp lại chúng càng nhiều càng tốt.